being a developer and working on Tech
can sometimes feel exhausting it is very
common for developers or people that are
studying to become developers to burn
out everything changes so quickly there
are new Frameworks libraries and updates
coming out all at the same time it can
feel hard and draining to keep up like
swimming against the current it's okay
to push hard from time to time but when
we overextend ourselves and push hard
for long periods of time is when we
start to burn out I personally haven't
burnt out but I have had periods of time
where I know I'm burning out and when
that happens I really make an effort on
stopping it before I burn out completely
I have seen people that burn out and
it's not pretty so we have to be careful
not to let it go to that point and stop
it before it's too late if you search
online the number one advice you might
see is that to stop yourself from
burning out you need to rest the problem
is that in my case that advice did not
work so what I found out is that instead
of resting what I have to do is to
recharge the way I see it resting and
recharging are two different things
resting is hard to Define recharging
that is easy to notice if after work I
lay down on my couch scrolling to
Twitter or Tick Tock you could say I'm
resting maybe but am I recharging no
after hours to scroll in through social
media I noticed that I don't actually
feel better maybe my body is not tired
but my brain isn't an even worse shape
than before and burning out or not in
our industry is all about keeping the
brain healthy so instead of just trying
to rest I try to do what recharges me
what makes me feel better what recharges
you and what recharges me might be very
different so if you know what recharges
you then go ahead and do that more power
to you if you're not sure about what
activity recharges you I would like to
suggest you try exercising exercising
does wonders for your brain it is like
brain food it literally helps your brain
learn and remember more if you have a
sport that you like and you are already
exercising then keep doing it but if
you're like me and find going to the gym
dull and boring I have a suggestion for
you which is what this video is about
about this video is about the sport that
I can confidently say changed my life
climbing climbing is such a cool sport
it not only makes you stronger and
healthier physically it also makes your
mind stronger it humbles you it makes
you face your fears to focus more to
problem solve and to be more mindful
more present there are many types of
climbing you can do as of today we my
wife and I have done bouldering indoors
lead climbing and top rope climbing
indoors and Outdoors indoor bouldering
is what most people that are into
climbing start with indoor bouldering is
what you do on a Climbing Gym where the
walls are not that high and all you need
are climbing shoes and chalk the walls
on the gym will have routes you have to
climb also known as problems and your
job is to climb all the way up usually
the routes are short between 5 to 10
moves and as they become harder the
holes become smaller are more far away
and you need more strength and balance
from your first session to in bouldering
you are going to be humbled when you
realize how weak your body you are also
going to fall and fail publicly in front
of strangers which will also make you
check your ego be comfortable showing
vulnerability not caring about what
people think and asking for help but
it's also very rewarding if you keep
coming back to the gym one day you will
be able to start doing moves you could
not do before and that is a really good
feeling another lovely thing about
climbing is that it does not feel like a
workout it is problem solving with your
body time flies when we go to the gym
the reason why I started climbing is
because I wanted to get rid of my fear
of heights so after many months of
indoor bouldering we moved to top rope
and Lead climbing indoor bouldering is
cool and is what we do the most often
but their routes are short and the style
of the route is moving away from rock
climbing and it's becoming more like
parkour with a lot of swinging jumping
and flying top rope and Lead climbing
are a form of climbing where you climb a
Long Tall route far away from the ground
these routes require more endurance than
indoor bouldering because their route
more moves where in bouldering you do 5
to 10 moves a top rope or lead root has
at least 20. the difference between top
rope and Lead climbing is that in top
rope your harness is connected to a rope
that has an anchor at the top of the
route only climbing as you go up you
have to connect the Rope to the anchors
all the way up which is very challenging
you don't only have to climb the route
but you also have to stop and clip the
Rope The Falls are also bigger you can
do top rope and Lead climbing both
indoors and Outdoors but I really really
recommend you find a way of doing it
Outdoors it's an amazing feeling to
climb on real Rock and to have to find
the holes as you go up the holes in the
gym are color marked so you know which
holes you can use on the rear Rock
everything can potentially be a hold you
have to discover them and it can get
scary when you can't find a hole you are
20 meters above the ground and your arms
are getting tired to climb long routes
indoors and Outdoors you will need a
partner and you will need to trust them
with your life as they will be the ones
giving you rope hold holding it and
bringing you down so it's also an
exercise on trust climbing long route is
a mental battle for me you need to be
able to stay calm when you're up there
you need to learn how to breathe and you
need to be rational and control your
monkey brain this happens to me a lot
while climbing I know I'm safe the Rope
is good then not is solid the anchor is
okay my wife is belaying me and is
grabbing the Rope but even though I know
these things I still get scared my
rational mind freaks out while the
rational mind is saying don't worry we
got this just keep going up breathe
you'll be fine but that feeling that
feeling after doing something my mind
was telling me I was not going to be
able to do is what I'm addicted to this
is a route in Bangkok that had easy
holes but that was just incredibly tall
the highest I've ever claimed I spent
more than 20 minutes just looking at it
from the ground I did not want to go up
it was a mental battle that happened
before I stepped up to the walk the
feeling when I finished that route the
feeling of proving my fears wrong is
something I wish everyone can get to
feel I'm still afraid of heights the
fear will never go away with thanks to
climbing I learned that I can do things
despite the fear and that is why I made
this video I know I never make personal
videos like this one and I understand if
this is not what you subscribed for but
I really wanted to share this beautiful
sport with you it will make you stronger
physically and mentally which may be
what you need to change your life
climbing is also an amazing way of
emptying your mind refreshing your brain
and forgetting about whatever problems
you have because when you're up on the
wall or the rock nothing matters just
the present moment and The Rock you have
in front of you thank you for watching
this video if you think it's valuable
please like it share it with your
friends and subscribe to the channel
give climbing a go and push yourself to
do something you're afraid of something
you think is impossible because of the
lies your mind tells you I believe in
you you got this also please don't
forget that if you want to learn to go
to for free click the link below where
you can take free courses on JavaScript
python react react native go dark
flutter and many others all for free
click the link below and I will see you
there
see you on the next one bye